In the last couple videos, we
在前面几个视频里
(字幕整理：中国海洋大学 黄海广,haiguang2000@qq.com )
talked about the ideas of
我们谈到几个概念
how, first, if you're
首先
given features for movies, you
如果给你几个特征表示电影
can use that to learn parameters data for users.
我们可以使用这些资料去获得用户的参数数据
And second, if you're given parameters for the users,
第二 如果给你用户的参数数据
you can use that to learn features for the movies.
你可以使用这些资料去获得电影的特征
In this video we're going
本节视频中
to take those ideas and put
我们将会使用这些概念
them together to come up
并且将它们合并成
with a collaborative filtering algorithm.
协同过滤算法 (Collaborative Filtering Algorithm)
So one of the things we worked
我们之前做过的事情
out earlier is that if
其中之一是
you have features for the
假如你有了电影的特征
movies then you can solve
你就可以解出
this minimization problem to find
这个最小化问题
the parameters theta for your users.
为你的用户找到参数 θ
And then we also
然后我们也
worked that out, if you
知道了
are given the parameters theta,
如果你拥有参数 θ
you can also use that to
你也可以用该参数
estimate the features x, and
通过解一个最小化问题
you can do that by solving this minimization problem.
去计算出特征 x
So one thing you
所以你可以做的事
could do is actually go back and forth.
是不停地重复这些计算
Maybe randomly initialize the parameters
或许是随机地初始化这些参数
and then solve for theta,
然后解出 θ
solve for x, solve for theta,
解出 x 解出 θ
solve for x. But, it
解出 x
turns out that there is a
但实际上呢
more efficient algorithm that doesn't
存在一个更有效率的算法
need to go back and forth
让我们不再需要再这样不停地
between the x's and the
计算 x 和 θ
thetas, but that can solve
而是能够将
for theta and x simultaneously.
x 和 θ 同时计算出来
And here it is. What we are going to do, is basically take
下面就是这种算法 我们所要做的
both of these optimization objectives, and
是将这两个优化目标函数
put them into the same objective.
给合为一个
So I'm going to define the
所以我要来定义
new optimization objective j, which
这个新的优化目标函数 J
is a cost function, that
它依然是一个代价函数
is a function of my features
是我特征 x
x and a function
和参数 θ
of my parameters theta.
的函数
And, it's basically the two optimization objectives
它其实就是上面那两个优化目标函数
I had on top, but I put together.
但我将它们给合在一起
So, in order to
为了把这个解释清楚
explain this, first, I want to point out that this
首先 我想指出
term over here, this squared
这里的这个表达式
error term, is the same
这个平方误差项
as this squared error term and the
和下面的这个项是相同的
summations look a little bit
可能两个求和看起来有点不同
different, but let's see what the summations are really doing.
但让我们来看看它们到底到底在做什么
The first summation is sum
第一个求和运算
over all users J and
是所有用户 J 的总和
then sum over all movies rated by that user.
和所有被用户评分过的电影总和
So, this is really summing over all
所以这其实是正在将
pairs IJ, that correspond
所有关于 (i,j) 对的项全加起来
to a movie that was rated by a user.
表示被用户评分过的电影
Sum over J says, for every
关于 j 的求和
user, the sum of
意思是 对每个用户
all the movies rated by that user.
关于该用户评分的电影的求和
This summation down here, just does things in the opposite order.
而下面的求和运算只是用相反的顺序去进行计算
This says for every movie
这写着关于每部电影 i
I, sum over all
求和 关于的是
the users J that have
所有曾经对它评分过的
rated that movie and so, you
用户 j
know these summations, both of these
所以这些求和运算
are just summations over all pairs
这两种都是对所有 (i,j) 对的求和
ij for which
其中
r of i J is equal to 1.
r(i,j) 是等于1的
It's just something over all the
这只是所有你有评分的用户
user movie pairs for which you have a rating.
和电影对而已
and so those two terms
因此 这两个式子
up there is just
其实就是
exactly this first term, and
这里的第一个式子
I've just written the summation here explicitly,
我已经给出了这个求和式子
where I'm just saying the sum
这里我写着
of all pairs IJ, such that
其为所有 r(i,j) 值为1的
RIJ is equal to 1.
(i,j) 对求和
So what we're going
所以我们要做的
to do is define a
是去定义
combined optimization objective that
一个我们想将其最小化的
we want to minimize in order
合并后的优化目标函数
to solve simultaneously for x and theta.
让我们能同时解出 x 和 θ
And then the other terms in
然后在这些优化目标函数里的
the optimization objective are this,
另一个式子是这个
which is a regularization in terms of theta.
其为 θ 所进行的正则化
So that came down here and
它被放到这里
the final piece is this
最后一部分
term which is
是这项式
my optimization objective for
是我 x 的优化目标函数
the x's and that became this.
然后它变成这个
And this optimization objective
这个优化目标函数 J
j actually has an interesting property
它有一个很有趣的特性
that if you were to hold
如果你假设
the x's constant and just
x 为常数
minimize with respect to the thetas then
并关于 θ 优化的话
you'd be solving exactly this problem,
你其实就是在计算这个式子
whereas if you were to do
反过来也一样
the opposite, if you were to
如果你把 θ 作为常量
hold the thetas constant, and minimize
然后关于 x
j only with respect to
求 J 的最小值的话
the x's, then it becomes equivalent to this.
那就与第二个式子相等
Because either this term
因为不管是这个部分
or this term is constant if
还是这个部分 将会变成常数
you're minimizing only the respective x's or only respective thetas.
如果你将它化简成只以 x 或 θ 表达的话
So here's an optimization
所以这里是
objective that puts together my
一个将我的 x 和 θ
cost functions in terms of x and in terms of theta.
合并起来的代价函数
And in order to
然后
come up with just one
为了解出
optimization problem, what we're going
这个优化目标问题
to do, is treat this
我们所要做的是
cost function, as a
将这个代价函数视为
function of my features
特征 x
x and of my user
和用户参数 θ 的
pro user parameters data and
函数
just minimize this whole thing, as
然后全部化简为
a function of both the
一个既关于 x
Xs and a function of the thetas.
也关于 θ 的函数
And really the only difference
这和
between this and the older
前面的算法之间
algorithm is that, instead
唯一的不同是
of going back and forth, previously
不需要反复计算
we talked about minimizing with respect
就像我们之前所提到的
to theta then minimizing with respect to x,
先关于 θ 最小化 然后关于 x 最小化
whereas minimizing with respect to theta,
然后再关于 θ 最小化
minimizing with respect to x and so on.
再关于 x 最小化...
In this new version instead of
在新版本里头
sequentially going between the
不需要不断地在 x 和 θ
2 sets of parameters x and theta,
这两个参数之间不停折腾
what we are going to do
我们所要做的是
is just minimize with respect
将这两组参数
to both sets of parameters simultaneously.
同时化简
Finally one last detail
最后一件事是
is that when we're learning the features this way.
当我们以这样的方法学习特征量时
Previously we have been using
之前我们所使用的
this convention that
前提是
we have a feature x0 equals
我们所使用的特征 x0
one that corresponds to an interceptor.
等于1 对应于一个截距
When we are using this
当我们以
sort of formalism where we're are actually learning the features,
这种形式真的去学习特征量时
we are actually going to do away with this convention.
我们必须要去掉这个前提
And so the features we are going to learn x, will be in Rn.
所以这些我们将学习的特征量 x 是 n 维实数
Whereas previously we had
而先前我们所有的
features x and Rn + 1 including the intercept term.
特征值x 是 n+1 维 包括截距
By getting rid of x0 we now just have x in Rn.
删除掉x0 我们现在只会有 n 维的 x
And so similarly, because the
同样地
parameters theta is in
因为参数 θ 是
the same dimension, we now
在同一个维度上
also have theta in RN
所以 θ 也是 n 维的
because if there's no
因为如果没有 x0
x0, then there's no need
那么 θ0
parameter theta 0 as well.
也不再需要
And the reason we do away
我们将这个前提移除的理由是
with this convention is because
因为我们现在是在
we're now learning all the features, right?
学习所有的特征 对吧?
So there is no need
所以我们没有必要
to hard code the feature that is always equal to one.
去将这个等于一的特征值固定死
Because if the algorithm really wants
因为如果算法真的需要
a feature that is always equal
一个特征永远为1
to 1, it can choose to learn one for itself.
它可以选择靠自己去获得1这个数值
So if the algorithm chooses,
所以如果这算法想要的话
it can set the feature X1 equals 1.
它可以将特征值 x1 设为1
So there's no need
所以没有必要
to hard code the feature of
去将1 这个特征定死
001, the algorithm now has
这样算法有了
the flexibility to just learn it by itself. So, putting
灵活性去自行学习
everything together, here is
所以 把所有讲的这些合起来
our collaborative filtering algorithm.
即是我们的协同过滤算法
first we are going to
首先我们将会把
initialize x and
x 和 θ
theta to small random values.
初始为小的随机值
And this is a little bit
这有点像
like neural network training, where there
神经网络训练
we were also initializing all the parameters of a neural network to small random values.
我们也是将所有神经网路的参数用小的随机数值来初始化
Next we're then going
接下来 我们要用
to minimize the cost function using
梯度下降 或者某些其他的高级优化算法
great intercepts or one of the advance optimization algorithms.
把这个代价函数最小化
So, if you take derivatives you
所以如果你求导的话
find that the great intercept
你会发现梯度下降法
like these and so this
写出来的更新式是这样的
term here is the
这个部分就是
partial derivative of the cost function,
代价函数
I'm not going to write that out,
这里我简写了
with respect to the feature
关于特征值 x(i)k 的偏微分
value Xik and similarly
然后相同地
this term here is also
这部分
a partial derivative value of
也是代价函数
the cost function with respect to the parameter
关于我们正在最小化的参数 θ
theta that we're minimizing.
所做的偏微分
And just as a reminder, in
提醒一下
this formula that we no
这公式里
longer have this X0 equals
我们不再有这等于1 的 x0 项
1 and so we have
所以
that x is in Rn and theta is a Rn.
x 是 n 维 θ 也是n 维
In this new formalism, we're regularizing
在这个新的表达式里
every one of our perimeters theta, you know, every one of our parameters Xn.
我们将所有的参数 θ 和 xn 做正则化
There's no longer the special
不存在 θ0
case theta zero, which was
这种特殊的情况 会需要不同地正则化
regularized differently, or which
或者说是
was not regularized compared to
跟 θ1 到 θn 的正则化
the parameters theta 1 down to theta.
不同的 θ0 的正则化
So there is now no longer a
所以现在不存在 θ0
theta 0, which is why
这就是为什么
in these updates, I did not
在这些更新式里
break out a special case for k equals 0.
我并没有分出 k 等于0的特殊情况
So we then use gradient descent
所以我们使用梯度下降
to minimize the cost function
来最小化这个
j with respect to the
代价函数 J
features x and with respect to the parameters theta.
关于特征 x 和参数 θ
And finally, given a
最后 给你一个用户
user, if a user
如果这个用户
has some parameters, theta, and
具有一些参数 θ
if there's a movie with
以及给你一部电影
some sort of learned features x,
带有已知的特征 x
we would then predict that that
我们可以预测
movie would be given a
这部电影会被
star rating by that user
θ 转置乘以 x
of theta transpose j. Or
给出怎样的评分
just to fill those in,
或者将这些直接填入
then we're saying that if user
那我们可以说
J has not yet
如果用户 j
rated movie I, then
尚未对电影 i 评分
what we do is predict that
那我们可以预测
user J is going to
这个用户 j
rate movie I according to
将会根据 θ(j) 转置乘以 x(i)
theta J transpose Xi.
对电影 i 评分
So that's the collaborative
所以这就是
filtering algorithm and if
协同过滤算法
you implement this algorithm you actually get a pretty
如果你使用这个算法
decent algorithm that will simultaneously
你可以得到一个十分有用的算法
learn good features for hopefully
可以同时学习
all the movies as well as
几乎所有电影的特征
learn parameters for all the
和所有用户参数
users and hopefully give
然后有很大机会
pretty good predictions for how
能对不同用户会如何对他们尚未评分的电影做出评??价
different users will rate different movies that they have not yet rated
给出相当准确的预测